Rally Day Files, 1885-
Smith College Archives
Rally Day Files
1885-[ongoing]
Smith College.
RG 80
9 boxes (2.88 linear ft.)
Smith College Archives Northampton, MA
College celebration. Contains convocation programs, texts of speeches, photographs, newspaper clippings, press releases, show programs and scripts,dance programs, tickets, and class songs.
Biographical Note
"The origins of Rally Day can be traced to a series of annual celebrations for George Washington's birthday, the first of which was held at Smith College in February 1876. Over time, these celebrations evolved from essentially social dinners or receptions into daylong college events. The addition of a 'rally' to the day in 1894 was eventually reflected in the name Rally Day, first used in 1906. The celebration is now held annually on the third Wednesday in February.
Through the years, students have sponsored and participated in a range of activities: rallies, debates, basketball rivalries, dramatic presentations, singing and dancing. The current tradition of sponsoring an event to benefit a charity began in 1918 when the Rally Day Show was held to raise funds for the Smith College Relief Unit serving in World War I France.
The Smith College Medal has been awarded to outstanding alumnae at Rally Day since 1973. The medalists have become an important part of the program, speaking prior to convocation in classes and afterward in conversations with students.
Dress at Rally Day has evolved as well. In 1944, the senior class began wearing its graduation caps and gowns to the convocation. The day still marks the first time the seniors publicly wear their gowns. In recent years, however, the caps have been replaced by inventive hats of the students' choosing (and sometimes of their own making), in keeping with the 'rallying' and spirited nature of the day." (From the Rally Day Convocation Program February 23, 2000)
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The majority of the material is composed of convocation programs, texts of speeches, photographs, newspaper clippings, press releases, show programs and scripts. The files also include dance programs, tickets, and class songs. There are only a few items documenting Rally Day before 1896.
All of the materials are arranged chronologically except the general files which are arranged alphabetically.
Additional materials located in the Audio Visual Collection include videos of Rally Day shows, long playing recordings of songs and shows, one digital audio tape of the Glee Club, and audio cassettes of convocation speeches, shows, and a few Smith College Medalists panel discussions. Refer to the audio visual catalogue for more information and locations. Student scrapbooks may also contain materials on Rally Day.
Organization of the Collection
This collection is organized into five series:
I. General
II. Newspaper Clippings And Press Releases
III. Photographs
VI. Convocation Texts
V. Rally Day Shows And Songs
Information on Use
Terms of Access and Use
All of the files are open to the public according to the regulations of the Smith College Archives.
Additions to the Collection
Additions to these records arrive in the College Archives on a regular basis. Please contact the College Archives for the most up-to-date information.
History of the Collection
The materials in the Rally Day files came to the College Archives as they were created by students and staff and as gifts from alumnae.
Search Terms
Smith College--Rally Day.; Smith College.
- Series I General (1885 -), 3 linear inches
  This series is arranged alphabetically by subject and chronologically within each file.
  The subseries convocation programs 1911 - the present makes up the bulk of this series. The convocation programs 1962 and later contain a brief history of Rally Day. Other materials included are a list of Rally Day speakers 1894 - 1988, dance programs 1891-1892, odes to George Washington written by students, a chronology of the history of Rally Day, 1875 - 1926, the script for a Rally Day stunt, and memorabilia. The earliest item in the Rally Day files is in the Memorabilia folder of this series. It is a small handmade card from 1885 with a list of famous men such as George Washington and some of their wives.
  - Alumnae invitations 1990- (Box 3085)
  - Committee memorandums 1989- (Box 3085)
  - Convocation programs 1911- (Box 3085)
  - Convocation speakers list 1894-1988 (Box 3085)
  - Dance programs 1891-1892 (Box 3085)
  - Flyers handed out at Rally Day events 1934- (Box 3085)
  - History (Box 3085)
  - Invitations to attend luncheon 1989- (Box 3085)
  - Memorabilia 1885- (Box 3085)
  - Memorandums to the faculty 1972- (Box 3085)
  - Odes 1911-1932 (Box 3085)
  - Programs for basketball games and the crowning of the Freshman President 1948-1962 (Box 3085)
  - Schedule of events 1971- (Box 3085)
  - Rally Day stunt n.d. (Box 3085)
- Series II Newspaper clippings and press releases (1894 - ), 2.5 linear inches
  This series is arranged chronologically.
  There are press releases and newspaper clippings for most, but not all years 1895 - the present. This series contains newspaper clippings, handwritten and typed press releases, biographical information on Rally Day speakers, short advances of speeches, and lists of Rally Day committees, crews, and performers. The newspaper clippings and press releases cover all aspects of Rally Day including speeches, Smith College Medalists, basketball games, shows, convocation, Rally Day committee members and performers, and dances. Newspaper articles are from national, local, and college publications. Most of the clippings are from Boston, New York, Connecticut, Western Massachusetts, and Smith College newspapers. Press coverage is heaviest in the 1930s and dwindling in the 1950s. After the 1950s, press coverage is mostly limited to local papers such as the Hampshire Gazette and Smith College publications. The full texts of speeches are located in SERIES VI. CONVOCATION TEXTS. Additional information on speakers after 1965 can be found in the Honorary Degrees Files.
  - Newspaper clippings and press releases 1894 - (Box 3085.1)
- Series III Photographs (1894 - ), 10 linear inches
  The photographs are arranged chronologically.
  They primarily feature the Rally Day shows, convocation, basketball games, students dressed up in costumes, and convocation speakers. Many of the early photographs feature Alumnae Gym where most of the Rally Day events took place. There is an early photograph of a student dressed up as George Washington (1896) and another dressed up as George Washington's slave (1895). Many of the newspaper clippings in SERIES II. NEWSPAPER CLIPPINGS AND PRESS RELEASES feature photographs.
  - Photographs 1894-1959 (Box 3085.2)
  - Photographs 1960 - (Box 3085.3)
  - Photographs n.d. (Box 3085.3)
- Series VI Convocation Texts (1930 - ), 2 linear inches
  The texts of Rally Day convocation speeches are arranged chronologically.
  Not every year's speech is included in the files. The biggest gaps are between 1951 and 1970, and 1972 and 1991. This series also includes the texts and a program for the 1970 Rally Day Symposium, "Is Today's Environment Tomorrow's Inheritance?"
  - Convocation texts 1930 - (Box 3086)
- Series V Rally Day Shows and Songs (1893 - ), 1.42 linear feet
  The files in this series are arranged chronologically.
  Most consist of programs, scripts for skits, scores and texts of songs sung at Rally Day shows. Although the Rally Day benefit shows did not start until 1918, concert programs and the texts of songs sung at Rally Day pre-1918 are included in this series. Many of the songs are written to the tunes of popular songs. The text of one Rally Day stunt, undated, is in SERIES I. GENERAL. See also Students, Dramatics 1880-1881 for the script and photographs of a Tertiumm Quid play Pinafore of the Revolution performed February 23, 1881.
  - Shows and songs 1887-1945 (Box 3087)
  - Shows and songs 1946-1959 (Box 3088)
  - Shows and songs 1960-1989 (Box 3089)
  - Shows and songs 1990- (Box 3089.1)
  - Shows and songs n.d. (Box 3089.1)